Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*.
Today's דף *daf* is י"ב *Yud Beis* and we pick up three
lines from the bottom on י"א עמוד ב' *Yud Alef Amud Beis*
and we're in the middle of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which is
seeing אחשוורוש Achashverosh *Achashveirosh* as doing a repetition of what בלשאצר *Belshazzar*
did, which was taking out the vessels of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* and using them. And that ties into our מנהג
*minhag* of the way we read כלים keilim מכלים שונים *keilim mikeilim
shonim* in a different טראפ trop *trop*, which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
will get to in a little bit. I mean not the טראפ
*trop*, but that it hinges it on that verse.
And is here hinging it on the interpretation of the verse ששת
המלך אחשוורוש Achashverosh *Shishat HaMelech Achashveirosh* after נתיישבה דעתו *nisyashva da'ato*, he
felt comfortable now that the prophecy of seventy years would not be
fulfilled. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explained that what was the prophecy?
So it said that one פסוק pasuk *pasuk* said seventy years לבבל
*Livavel*, another פסוק posuk *pasuk* said לחורבות ירושלים Yerushalayim, *lacharvos Yerushalayim* of
the destruction of Jerusalem, which we'll get to. But the one of
לבבל *Livavel*, so seventy years if he's paid from נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nevuchadnezzar*
to בלשאצר *Belshazzar*'s third year was seventy years. נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar
*Nevuchadnezzar* was forty-five years king plus twenty-three of אויל מרודך Evil Merodach
*Evil Merodach*. What did I write here, thirty-seven?
No, I'm sorry. How much was that? I thought it was twenty-three.
אויל מרודך Evil Merodach *Evil Merodach*, this is thirty-seven from a particular
date, I think. Anyway בלשאצר *Belshazzar* was, one minute,
I think I'm right, hold on, yeah twenty-three. Alright, I don't know
what this thirty-seven was referring to, I reconstructed it but anyway. נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar *Nevuchadnezzar* was forty-five years, אויל מרודך Evil Merodach *Evil Merodach* was
twenty-three. Not exactly clear where some of these numbers are coming from,
but that adds up to sixty-eight and בלשאצר *Belshazzar* on his third
year, I mean sixty-seven and בלשאצר *Belshazzar* on his third year, that
made seventy. So that was when בלשאצר *Belshazzar* took out the vessels
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* and he was slain
in the middle of the night. So comes אחשוורוש Achashverosh. *Achashveirosh* and
אחשוורוש Achashverosh, *Achashveirosh* says no no no, your problem was that you
were counting from the beginning of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar. *Nevuchadnezzar* and what you
should have been doing is you should have been counting from the
beginning of the exile of בבל Bavel *Bavel* which is גלות יכניה
*Galus Yechonyah* which gives him eight more years. So there's eight more
years was five, was one more year of בלשאצר *Belshazzar* because it's
in his third year. Five years the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says now
we're in מדי ופרס Madai uParas? *Madai u'Paras*, this is בבל Bavel
*Bavel* and כשדים *Chasdim*. So five years of דריוש Daryavesh *Daryavesh* and
כורש Koresh. *Koresh* which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asserts, doesn't tell you
how it knows it,
that makes six plus two years of אחשוורוש Achashverosh. *Achashveirosh* and then
in his third year you had him taking out the vessels of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. So that's how the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* got seventy if you count from here as opposed to
seventy counting from there and
that's where we ended with
yesterday. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
והא שפיר חשיב *ve'ha shapir chashiv*, three lines from the bottom. So
I don't understand, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, he did the math
well. So it seems to have been seventy years if you start
from this exile of גלות יכניה *Galus Yechonyah*. Of course there's other
places you could start from which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will get
to, but let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, איהו נמי מיטעי *ihu nami miet'ei*, he also made a mistake
in the seventy years. דאיבעי ליה למני מחורבות ירושלים *d'iba'ei lei limni
mechurvas Yerushalayim*, right? Because the other פסוק posuk. *pasuk* says לחורבות ירושלים
*lacharvos Yerushalayim* of the destruction to the destruction of Jerusalem. One פסוק
posuk. *pasuk* says from ירמיהו *Yirmiyahu* seventy years from בבל Bavel. *Bavel*,
but another פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in דניאל Daniel *Daniel* says seventy years
from the destruction of Jerusalem which was גלות צדקיהו *Galus Tzidkiyahu* was
חורבן הבית *churban habayis*. So he should have counted seventy from here
and not seventy from there. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says סוף
סוף כמה בצירן חסרי *sof sof kama batziran chasrei*. Okay,
but what's the difference between eight? יכניה *Yechonyah* was year eight of
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar. *Nevuchadnezzar* and צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu* was year nineteen, so the difference
is eleven years later. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says when you
got to year three of אחשוורוש Achashverosh. *Achashveirosh* that was seventy, seventy
from גלות יכניה *Galus Yechonyah*.
Now it says it should have been not seventy, he should have
waited till seventy from גלות צדקיהו *Galus Tzidkiyahu*. Fine, that was eleven
years later. He should have counted the seventy from here, from the
destruction of Jerusalem, so he should have waited till down here, seventy
years later would have been חורבות ירושלים *charvos Yerushalayim*. Okay, so how
much more is that? That's eleven more years, right? From eight to
nineteen is eleven. So אחשוורוש Achashverosh, *Achashveirosh* should have waited till his
fourteenth year. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say
but there's a problem because in the fourteenth year of אחשוורוש Achashverosh,
*Achashveirosh* he was still king as we know from the מגילה Megilla
*Megillah*, the Jews had not yet returned to ארץ ישראל Yisrael *Eretz
Yisrael*. So this math doesn't work either. Says I get that you
say אחשוורוש Achashverosh *Achashveirosh* made a mistake and he thought that the
seventy years was up and he got punished and בלשאצר *Belshazzar* made
a mistake and he got punished. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
even if you count the seventy years from the latest possible date,
from the destruction of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, you're
only going to get to year fourteen of אחשוורוש *Achashveirosh*, so there
wasn't, the גאולה Geulah *geulah* didn't happen at that point. stage. So
let's take a look. סוף סוף כמה בתר חשבי איהו כמה מלך
how long was אחשוורוש king? ארבסרי Arbasrei fourteen right if you look
in the מגילה Megillah. right? ובארבסרי דידיה איבעי ליה למיבני בית
המקדש U'v'arbasrei didei ibayei leih limivnei Beis HaMikdash in the 14th year
of אחשוורוש the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. should have been rebuilt based
on this math. So the latest you'll get will be year 14
of אחשוורוש. אלא מה כתיב Ala mah kesiv what does the verse
say? באדין בטילת עבידת בית אלהא Be'adayin batilas avidas beis Elaha at
that time was negated,
like a cease, the working on the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. די
בירושלם di b'Yerushalem in ירושלם Yerushalem in Jerusalem. Now this פסוק pasuk
is in the time of כורש. Koresh Back here כורש Koresh initially
allowed for the beginning of the rebuilding of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, right? And then it got negated, and that got reversed, and
that got reversed post אחשוורוש, okay? So the rebuilding of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash we'll talk about in a minute but it happened
here, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says and it stopped here, okay?
So בטילת, batilas, you remember
also בטילת. batilas. Okay, so anyway, so there was no rebuilding, so
how could you say the גאולה Geulah happened here? The actual rebuilding
only started after אחשוורוש. So the גמרא Gemara. says let's take a
look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא Amar Rava said
רבא Rava שני מקוטעות הוו. shanim mekuta'os havu. Okay,
the years were not full years, meaning when we did this whole
math and we said, you know, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar was 45 years and
אויל מרודך Evil Merodach, 23,
so those were in his 45th year of being king he died
and אויל מרודך took over. And אויל מרודך was king for 23
years and then he died and בלשצר Belshazzar took over. But that
doesn't mean that this was a full 45 years and this was
a full 23 years, right? This king took over in the middle
of this year and the next king took over in the middle
of that year. So you can't just add these years up. The
last year of all of these things are non-full years. So actually
you're like one or two years off. And so let's take a
look, so the גמרא Gemara says תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi
we taught similarly ויתר שנה אחת לבלשצר. v'yeser shana achas l'Belshazzar. There
was another year when בלשצר Belshazzar thought he was in year 70
but that wasn't year 70 from the beginning of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar because
there were partial years here. So even after בלשצר Belshazzar died, there
was one more year before you got to be year 70 of
בבל Bavel when דריוש Daryavesh took over. ועמד דריוש והשלימה V'amad Daryavesh
v'hishlima and
then when דריוש Daryavesh, took over, he really got you to year
70. And that's when, and then when כורש Koresh took over, this
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say, כורש Koresh. then
gave them the initial permission to rebuild and then he reversed it.
So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is like this: the counting
was close but it was off by a year or two, okay?
So בלשצר Belshazzar thought he had hit year 70. Problem was, he
added these numbers together, 45 and 23 and 2, and those weren't
full years, there was a year or two left to get to
70. So that year or two to get to 70 from בבל
Bavel. happened in the time of כורש. Koresh, כורש, Koresh there was
a partial גאולה geulah there. כורש Koresh gave them permission to begin
rebuilding, okay? And that's the one verse that says 70 years from
בבל. Bavel, Okay, then כורש Coresh, reversed it. Then you have the
אחשוורוש. Now by, after אחשוורוש, then you had the, that was an
additional, you know, 18 years or so. Then after אחשוורוש, not in
year 14, because we now have gained a year or two, then
you have the 70 years. So this is 70 years from בבל
Bavel and then after אחשוורוש is 70 years from חרבות ירושלים charvos
Yerushalayim and then the rebuilding started in earnest and that was the
second prophecy.
Okay, so let's read that.
The גמרא Gemara says, yes?
You alluded to the fact that these years are counted from a
specific date.
Yeah,
meaning it's from how many years they have been king and not
how many total years have passed.
So the numbering is not based on their anniversary, it's based upon
when those months?
No, I think it is based on their
anniversary. ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right. But if נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar was king
for 45 years but he was two months into his 45th year
and he died,
and then you'll say the next guy was king for 23 years
but the first year you're counting is the last 10 months, so
you've double-counted a year.
So you're using different numbers? Right. Okay.
Well, how do
you
know the 70 is based upon an actual anniversary?
You mean actual like calendar year? Yes, that's what you wrote. Or
do you mean a 12-month period?
Right, I mean, obviously, anyway, 70 could also still be just totally
symbolic as 70 is a symbolic number. But you're right, I mean
the גמרא Gemara could have I guess got to that if it
needed to, but what the גמרא Gemara is saying is a reasonable
point. The 70 years of the prophecy is 70 calendar
years. This is just saying
that
the שיבת ציון Shivat Tziyon was 140 years or however you understand
the events the year 140 years since the...
No, no, no, no, this 70 is not 70 from
here. This 70 is 70 from חרבות ירושלים Charvot Yerushalayim and this
70 is 70 from
בבל. Bavel, Right, two reckonings, one from בבל, Bavel one from here.
So אחשורוש Achashverosh was pretty close except he made two mistakes. A,
he double-counted a year, so it really it began in the time
two years later in the time of כורש, Coresh number one. And
number two, that wasn't the full redemption, that was the beginning of
the redemption. Then אחשורוש Achashverosh made a mistake as he counted from
over here but anyway and he should have counted from down here
which would have got you right after אחשורוש Achashverosh and that was
70 from בבל Bavel, and that got you to the real beginning
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash Do we have
corroborating evidence to support that כורש Coresh. changed his mind?
Yes, that actually is a פסוק pasuk in עזרא Ezra that, that's
what the גמרא gemara, quoted there at the bottom. בטיל עבידת בית
אלהא די בירושלם. Betel avidat beit elaha di vi-Yerushalayim.
That was the ביטול. bittul.
Yes, exactly. That's a מפורש meforash פסוק. pasuk? Right, that's a מפורש
meforash פסוק. pasuk.
Okay. All right. So the גמרא gemara says like this. Okay. And
this, by the way, and to make it more confusing, and I'm
sure that Charles can tell us about this because I have no
idea how this works with any other reckoning, but anyway, this is
in the פסוקים psukim in עזרא, Ezra, here the rebuilding afterwards that
gets done in earnest is דריוש, Daryavesh. which the גמרא gemara assumes
means the second דריוש. Daryavesh This is the first דריוש Daryavesh and
this is the second דריוש Daryavesh. and the גמרא Gemara also assumes
that he was the child of אחשורוש Achashverosh and אסתר, Esther, just
so you should know. Okay, which our גמרא Gemara is going to
say, but another גמרא Gemara does. Okay. So this was the real
rebuilding 70 years from חרבות ירושלים, Charvot Yerushalayim, this was the beginning
of the process 70 years from נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnetzar.
Yeah, that's after אויל מרודך, none of this coincides with anything.
Okay, fine. All right, so let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara אמר רבא אף דניאל טעה
בהאי חושבנא. Amar Rava af Daniel ta'ah be-hai chushbana. This was so
complicated even דניאל Daniel made mistakes, didn't get it exactly right. 70
years from when, how do you count the years? דכתיב, De-chtiv, the
verse says, בשנת אחת למלכו אני דניאל בינתי בספרים. Bishnat achat le-malcho
ani Daniel binnoti ba-sefarim. At the first year of his king, I
דניאל Daniel investigated into the books, looked into the books. ומדאמר בינתי,
U-mi-d'amar binnoti, I paid, I gave my, I explored, I investigated, I
looked closely. מכלל דטעה, Miklal de-ta'ah,
obviously he had made some mistake and he had to like re-explore
the פסוקים psukim in order to re-analyze the פסוקים psukim in order
to determine what the 70 years would be. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מכל מקום קשו קראי אהדדי. Mi-kol makom kashu kra'ei a-hadadi. We
got a problem with the פסוקים. psukim. כתיב, Ktiv, I already sort
of gave you the answer to this. One verse says מלאות לבבל,
Milo'at le-Vavel, 70 years will be filled to בבל, which presumably means
from the beginning of נבוכדנצר. וכתיב, U-chtiv, another verse says לחרבות ירושלים,
Le-charvot Yerushalayim, to the destruction of Jerusalem. So אמר רבא לפקידה בעלמא.
Amar Rava le-pekidah b'alma.
No, the first 70 years from בבל is a just a slight
remembering when the process began and that as we said was in
the time of כורש. Coresh It wasn't the full redemption which occurred
later after אחשורוש Achashverosh in the time of דריוש. והיינו, Ve-hainu, and
as we know, that redemption of כורש Coresh himself reversed it, it
didn't even last. והיינו דכתיב, Ve-hainu de-chtiv, and here's the verse in
עזרא Ezra where they give the permission to begin the rebuilding. כה
אמר כורש מלך פרס כל ממלכות הארץ נתן לי השם אלהי השמים
והוא פקד עלי לבנות לו בית בירושלם. Koh amar Coresh melech Paras
kol mamlechot ha-aretz natan li Hashem elokei ha-shamayim ve-hu pakad alai livnot
lo bayit bi-Yerushalayim. Thus says כורש Coresh, the king of Persia. All
the kingdoms of the lands, השם Hashem the God of heavens has
given me
and He has appointed me, and there's the word פקד pakad and
פקידה pekidah of רבא, Rava, to build for him a house in
Jerusalem. So therefore that was that began 70 years from בבל, but
the actual rebuilding began 70 years from the destruction of Jerusalem after
אחשורוש. Achashverosh. דרש רב נחמן בר רב חסדא מאי דכתיב. Darash Rav
Nachman bar Rav Chisda mai de-chtiv. What's meant by the verse in
ישעיהו? Yeshayahu?
כה
אמר השם למשיחו לכורש אשר החזקתי בימינו. Koh amar Hashem li-meshicho le-Choresh
asher hachazakti vi-ymino. Thus says God to his anointed one, to כורש,
Coresh that I have strengthened his right hand. וכי כורש משיח הוה.
Ve-chi Coresh
mashiach hava.
Was כורש Coresh. really the משיח? Mashiach? Now, משיח Mashiach here doesn't
necessarily mean with a
capital M, but it means he's been anointed.
In the context of the verse, he was chosen and anointed to
begin the rebuilding of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash But the גמרא
Gemara. takes offense at this label. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא
אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשיח. Ela amar lo ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu
le-mashiach. No, משיח Mashiach is not כורש. Coresh It's כה אמר השם
למשיחו. Koh amar Hashem li-meshicho. Thus says God to his Messiah regarding
כורש אשר החזקתי בימינו, Choresh asher hachazakti vi-ymino,
regarding כורש Coresh. who I've strengthened his right hand. strengthened his right
hand. רש"י Rashi actually says that if you read the טראפ closely,
there seems to be a clear distinction between משיחו Mishicho and כורש.
Coresh. Anyway, קובל אני לך על כורש. Covel ani lecha al Coresh.
I have a complaint to you about כורש. Coresh So God is
complaining to משיח Mashiach that כורש Coresh who was supposed to presumably
begin the process didn't do the job fully. אני אמרתי הוא יבנה
ביתי. Ani amarti hu yivneh beiti. I said he would build my
house. Okay? He would be the one to actually rebuild it. ויקבץ
גליותי Vekabeitz galiyosai
and he would gather the exiles. That sounds pretty much like the
job of משיח. Mashiach. והוא אמר Vehu amar but כורש Coresh said
מי בכם מכל עמו ויעל. Mi vachem mikol amo vaya'al. He didn't
actually actively rebuild it, actively gather the exile, he just gave the
Jews permission to rebuild it. He didn't live up to what the
plan had been. So in two ways it's sort of saying כורש
Coresh. wasn't משיח. Mashiach. Number one, it's he didn't live up to
the plan, and number two, it reads the verse to distinguish משיחו
Mishicho from כורש. Coresh But it is interesting because the way it
sort of says at least what the plan was, it sounds a
lot like what the job of משיח Mashiach is.
Yes, כורש Coresh is being treated more strictly by this commentary than
הושע Hoshea the last king of the Northern Kingdom. Yeah. When הושע
Hoshea took down the sentries that kept Jews from going to ירושלים,
he's praised for that even though he didn't order people to go,
but the Jewish people who didn't go after he took down the
border guards
are criticized and there's commentary say that was the final nail in
the coffin of the Northern Kingdom. So כורש is being criticized more
severely.
Right, I mean it's not saying what he, I mean I think
it's saying he did a lot of good, but it's just saying
it's sort of like the גמרא Gemara, about חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, right? That
he could have been the משיח Mashiach had he said שירה shira
after, you know,
סנחריב. Sancheriv. Just saying he didn't live up to the potential to
the actual what the ultimate vision had been. Okay, anyway that's the
end of figuring out the 70 years, but it situates this whole
story of פורים Purim in that larger context of that prophecy and
the גאולה and anticipating it and so on. Okay, now back to
the מגילה. megillah. חיל פרס ומדי. Cheil Paras uMadai.
The, you know, the, what, the officers of פרס
ומדי. Paras uMadai. הפרתמים. Hapartamim. So the again הפרתמים Partamim which are
somehow the governors, the officers. דכתיב Dechtiv in the other verse says
למלכי מדי ופרס, Lemalchei Madai uParas, to the kings of מדי Madai
and פרס. Paras. So the problem of the גמרא Gemara is first
of all which is first, is it פרס ומדי Paras uMadai or
מדי ופרס? Madai uParas רש"י Rashi points out that the question is
which is coming from פרס. Paras. Is it the מלכי מדי ופרס
malchei Madai uParas or the kings coming from מדי Madai because מלכי
malchei is juxtaposed to מדי? Madai? Or is it the חיל פרס?
cheil Paras? Or I mean or is it מדי הפרתמים? Madai hapartamim?
Or is it that the, you know, more like the governors are
coming from מדי Madai but not the kings? אמר רבא Amar Rava
אסתנויי אסתין בהדדי. Astinuyei astin behadadi. The Medians and the Persians sort
of made an agreement between them. אי מינן מלכי, Ei minan malchei,
if the kings come from us, מינייכו אפרכי, minaichu epharchi, from you
will come the governors of the provinces. ואי מינייכו מלכי, V'ei minaichu
malchei, and if the kings come from you, מינן אפרכי, minan epharchi,
from us will come the governors. So these were two, you know,
these were two kingdoms that got together to rule over the world
and they basically split the, you know, split the positions of power
between them. Power sharing. Exactly. Okay. Now, בהראותו את עושר כבוד
מלכותו, Beharoso es osher kvod malchuso, when he demonstrated the wealth of
the glory of his kingdom. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא Amar Rabi
Yosi bar Chanina מלמד שלבש בגדי כהונה. melamed shelavash bigdei kehuna. So
now picking up on the theme of taking out the כלים keilim
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash what he also did at this
party was he dressed the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. So here basically
he is trying to usurp, you know, the power of God, like
saying basically I have control over the vessels, I'm going to wear
the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. and so on.
And, you know, and sort of like I think that again it
could just be each one of these פסוקים pesukim that the גמרא
Gemara is just saying what it has to say and they don't
necessarily tie together to some overarching theme. Oh look, it says מדי
Madai ופרס and פרס ומדי, Paras uMadai, so let's say something. Is
it this or is it that, let's say something. But if one
tries to connect some theme, you know, there seems to be here
a little bit of an undermining of the haughtiness of אחשורוש. Achashveirosh.
Here he is taking out the vessels, here he is he's wearing
the בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. At the same time, like, you know,
we said before, how did he even get to be king, did
he really deserve it, did he buy his way there? There's all
anyway an agreement between מדי Median and פרס. Paras. You know, all
of this is not about אחשורוש, Achashveirosh, it's like all about these
other sort of like powers and, you know, he's not as great
as he thinks and nevertheless here's all the things that he's doing.
I think you could read these in juxtaposition. Anyway, here's what it
says. כתיב הכא Ketiv hacha here it says יקר תפארת גדולתו, yekar
tiferes gedulaso, the glory, you know, the honor of the glory of
his greatness. וכתיב התם Uchtiv hasham and it says there by the
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna לכבוד ולתפארת. lechavod uletiferes. So again you have
that word of תפארת tiferes and כבוד kavod is, יקר yekar is
the Aramaic of כבוד kavod as the גמרא Gemara, said earlier. Okay,
so here he is he's usurping all of
these... honors and roles. ובמלואת הימים האלה, U'vimlos hayamim haeileh, when these
days were filled, right, עשה המלך, asah hamelech, you know, לכל העם
הנמצאים lechol ha'am hanimtzaim he made a big hundred and eighty day
feast. רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel, חד אמר מלך פיקח היה, chad amar
melech pike'ach hayah, one says he was a smart king, וחד אמר
vechad amar famous גמרא, Gemara מלך טיפש היה, melech tipesh hayah, he
was a stupid king. מאן דאמר מלך פיקח היה, Man de'amar melech
pike'ach hayah, he was a smart king, שפיר עבד דקריב רחיקי ברישא
shafir avad de'kariv richakei bereisha דבני מדינה כל אימת דבעי מפייס להו.
de'vnei medina kol eimas de'baei miphayes lehu. First, it was smart. First
he had a party for all of the distant provinces, get the
people that are less under your control, you know, first worry to
curry their favor. And then the last party was only for you
know, for for those that you know, for his own city because
the people of your own city you can worry about later, you
know, whenever you want, they're there, they're available in order to you
know if you need to if you need to make if you
need to cultivate them. ומאן דאמר טיפש היה, U'man de'amar tipesh hayah,
the one that says he was stupid, איבעי ליה לקרובי בני מדינה
ברישא. ibayei lei le'karuvi bnei medina bereisha. No, first you work at
cultivating those people of your own city, דאי מרדו ביה הנך, de'i
mardu beih hanach, הנך הוו קיימי בהדיה, hanach havu kaimei bahadeih, because
if the distant provinces rebel against you, at least your own countrymen
and the people of your own city will be with you. So
therefore, you know, he should have solidified his power base before he
worried about bringing in those distant people.
Okay. שאלו תלמידיו את רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Sha'alu talmidav es Rabi
Shimon bar Yochai. Now we're diverting taking a moment off from the
פסוק pasuk to have a like a little theological speculation. The students
asked רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabi Shimon bar Yochai, מפני מה נתחייבו
שונאיהם של ישראל שבאותו הדור כליה? mipnei mah nischayvu soneihem shel Yisrael
she'be'oso hador kilah? Why did the enemies of the Jews, meaning the
Jews in that generation, why were they deserving of destruction? What did
they do that was deserving of the גזירת המן? gzeiras Haman? אמר
להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, אמרו אתם, imru atem, what
do you think? אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to him, מפני
שנהנו מסעודתו של אותו רשע, mipnei she'nehenu mi'se'udaso shel oso rasha, because
of the opening story of the מגילה. Megillah. They were all part
of that
party, and אחשורוש Achashverosh is being called אותו רשע. oso rasha. They
were all part of the party, which
presumably means they were eating טרייף, treif, but it means that A,
they were either assimilating, which is one issue that חז"ל Chazal bring
up a lot, or B, it means that they were you know,
complicit in all of the machinations that the king was doing, that
it's the issue of the רשע. rasha. Although again, it's not clear
which of those two is sort of being emphasized here. It seems
it seems more it should be the issue of assimilation, but the
emphasis of סעודתו של אותו רשע se'udaso shel oso rasha seems more
an issue about sort of being complicit in some of the political
machinations of אחשורוש. Achashverosh. So the גמרא Gemara says, אם כן שבשושן
יהרגו שבכל העולם כולו אל יהרגו. im kein she'be'Shushan yeiharagu she'be'chol ha'olam
kulo al yeiharagu. If that's true, then only the Jews in שושן
Shushan should have been killed, only the ones that actually actively participated,
not the ones that were more distant. Okay, so it's funny because
it says that he made a party right for everybody. שושן Shushan
was only the last week. Not exactly clear what the challenge was
here.
Anyway, אמרו לו, amru lo, so they said back to him, אמור
אתה, emor atah, okay, so you tell us, what do you think?
אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said back to them, מפני שהשתחוו לצלם,
mipnei she'hishtachavu la'tzelem, because they bowed down to the idol. רש"י Rashi
says this is going back to the story in נבוכדנצר where everybody
was prepared to bow down to the idol except חנניה מישאל ועזריה,
Chananya Mishael va'Azarya, which was a little while earlier. But אמרו לו,
amru lo, so they said to him, וכי משוא פנים יש בדבר?
ve'chi maso panim yesh ba'davar? Would there therefore be any lifting up
of the face, meaning would there be any forgiveness? If that was
their sin, how would they get the miracle done for them? Why
should they be forgiven for the sin of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
אמר להם, Amar lahem, so he said back to them, הם לא
עשו אלא לפנים, heim lo asu ela lifnim, or they only did
it for like appearance's sake. Okay, it's interesting, לפנים lifnim sometimes you
think means inner, what's on the inside, but also פנים, panim, the
face of things. They only did it for appearances. They didn't really
believe in this idol. They bowed down because נבוכדנצר was forcing them.
So it was only external, it was only for appearance's sake. And
therefore they didn't really deny God and therefore God was willing to
do this miracle for him.
אף הקדוש ברוך הוא לא עשה עמהם אלא לפנים.
Af
ha'Kadosh Baruch
Hu lo asah imahem ela lifnim.
Right, exactly. As I said, they were forced.
So therefore God also, when He brought the threat of המן, Haman,
it was only appearances, it was not something that was like a
really you know inner deep and going to happen, it was only
the appearance of it and then it was waved away.
והיינו דכתיב, Ve'hainu de'chsiv, that's meant by the verse, כי לא ענה
מלבו. ki lo inah mi'libo. God does not bring suffering, does not
desire suffering from His heart. But presumably the point here is is
that it is not if it's not coming מלבו mi'libo from the
heart of a person the sin if it was only external then
God is not going to punish you or you know or
fully for that type of a transgression. Now this obviously is a
very challenging גמרא Gemara because this basically describes mostly what the realities
have always been in the times of martyrdom is that you're asked
to the Jews have to baptize themselves or to accept Muhammad or
to you know whatever it was in the time of of אחשורוש
Achashverosh and it's not like they really would have converted at that
time or really would have denied God, they would have done it
because they were being forced. And it would have been only an
external show. And nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara says, well, okay, so therefore
could be forgiven. So this actually is very important because it raises
the question of if a Jew does not live up to the
demands of martyrdom, what type of sin have he or she performed?
And תוספות Tosafot says just in a passing comment, but it is
actually the central point of the רמב"ם Rambam in his אגרת תימן
Iggeret Teiman where he deals with Jews that basically
accepted Islam rather than convert. And he makes the point that he
says, okay, but the sin that you've performed is that you haven't
done the מצוה mitzvah of קידוש השם, Kiddush Hashem, but you haven't
done the sin of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, because you're אנוס anous
in עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. You worshipped עבודה זרה avodah zarah because
there was a gun to your head. So when there's a מצוה
mitzvah to give up your life, that's the מצוה, mitzvah, קידוש השם.
Kiddush Hashem. And if you didn't do it, you didn't do קידוש
השם, Kiddush Hashem, but it doesn't mean you transgressed עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. You were completely אנוס. anous. And there was no belief that
was behind it, and there was no desire that was behind it
and so on. And therefore, it's something that it's not like the
most unforgivable sin. It can be forgiven. Right? And that was basically
רמב"ם Rambam's response in אגרת תימן. Iggeret Teiman. Now of course that
raises challenging political questions because you want the people not to be
completely lost, you want to bring them back. And therefore you want
to have more of an open and welcoming policy. But if you're
a little bit too open and welcoming then you might be encouraging
people the next time around to also not martyr them, and you
could say well okay that'll keep them alive. But no, what it
actually will lead to is that it'll lead to them being completely
lost to Judaism, because how many people are going to leave and
then come back? So it raises very interesting policy and leadership questions.
But the principle that if they actually submit and do עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it's not the worst sin in the world, it's not
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it might be a failure of קידוש השם,
Kiddush Hashem, but it's not עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, and therefore maybe
can be forgiven, that seems to definitely be the פשט pshat of
this סוגיא. sugya. Yes.
My understanding with the גמרא Gemara is saying is that just as
they didn't really mean it, God didn't really mean it either. Right.
In other words, God always knew all along that no one was
ever going to be killed by המן. Haman. Right. So theologically the
problem is, I guess during the Crusades God really did mean it.
Right, right. I mean, that's a good point. That's a very good
point. But yes, the גמרא Gemara does seem to be saying that
at least at this stage, it was all appearance, it wasn't going
to happen. And I should add another part of this is not
only the parallel of for them it was only external, the threat
therefore was only what it appeared to be and not genuine, but
I think the other parallel here is also the idea of הסתר
פנים hester panim in the נס nes of the מגילה. Megillah? That
God's action also was hidden, what was expressed, what was visible, everything
was what was visible on the surface. What was really happening on
the inside, God's invisible hand, that was the מידה כנגד מידה middah
k'neged middah parallel, the same way when the Jews worshipped עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, that was on the outside, that wasn't what was actually
at a deeper level truly happening. So I think there's a parallel
to the sort of נס נסתר nes nistar that's going on here
as well. David, you had a question?
How does it go from שונאיהם של ישראל son'eihem shel Yisrael to
representing Jews?
It sounds like
שונאיהם של ישראל son'eihem shel Yisrael is always the euphemism. Yes. שונאיהם
של תלמידי חכמים, son'eihem shel talmidei chachamim, שונאיהם של, son'eihem shel, sometimes
it's even שונאיהם של הקדוש ברוך הוא, son'eihem shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu,
שונאיהם של ישראל. son'eihem shel Yisrael. It's always a way of because
you don't want to say something bad about the Jews, so you
say it's about the non-Jews, but it's an understood euphemism. It's like
סגי נהור sagi nahor which is for a blind person, which is
the person who has... the phrase for the גמרא Gemara for a
blind person is סגי נהור, sagi nahor, the person of plentiful light.
All right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay.
בחצר גינת ביתן המלך. Bachatzar ginat bitan hamelech. So where we did
the whole party and now the... we've introduced this question whether אחשורוש
Achashveirosh is חכם chacham or טיפש. tipesh. By the way, that's a
real question in terms of just forgetting this issue about the distant
provinces and the near provinces, you know, the whole story with המן.
Haman. Right, was אחשורוש Achashveirosh just completely being manipulated? How do you
read the מגילה? Megillah I mean to me the פשט pshat of
the מגילה Megilla is אחשורוש Achashveirosh is being manipulated by whoever's the
next person up to bat. First he's manipulated by המן, Haman, then
he's manipulated by אסתר Esther and so on, but you could read,
again, to this issue about like לפנים, lifnim, that maybe he allows
himself to appear that way, and maybe he really is,
has a hidden agenda to all of what's going on.
It makes me think of Franklin Roosevelt also. And you have to
wonder who sets the agenda as to who's going to be the
last voice.
Interesting. What?
I meant the chief of staff who has all the power. No,
it was the last voice.
Is that what he was saying? He was saying he could appear...
anyway, fine. All right, let's go on. בחצר גינת ביתן המלך. Bachatzar
ginat bitan hamelech.
רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel. Okay, so which was it? Where was the
party? Was it in the court? Was it in the yard? Was
it in the garden? Was it in the castle? Literally it's in
the yard of the garden of the castle. רב ושמואל. Rav u'Shmuel.
חד אמר הראוי לחצר לחצר. Chad amar hara'uy l'chatzer l'chatzer. People that
were at the מדריגה, madreigah, the level of honor that they, the
lower level... that they only could be in the courtyard, they were
put into the courtyard area, הראוי לגינה לגינה, ha-rauy le-gina le-gina,
those that were at a higher level went to the garden, were
put in the garden area, הראוי לביתן לביתן, ha-rauy le-beisan le-beisan, and
those that were at the level that could be in the castle,
they got the party inside the castle. וחד אמר, ve-chad amar, the
other one says no, הושיבן בחצר ולא החזיקתן, hoshivan be-chatzer ve-lo hechzikasan,
first
he tried to have everybody the party in the courtyard. It didn't
fit, there were too many people, so בגינה, be-gina, so he moved
them to the garden, ולא החזיקתן, ve-lo hechzikasan, there were too many
for the garden, עד שהכניסן לביתן, ad she-hichnisan le-beisan,
until he finally brought them into the castle והחזיקתן. ve-hechzikasan. Okay, במתניתא
תנא, be-masnisa tana, הושיבן
בחצר, hoshivan be-chatzer, they were really all in the courtyard, ופתח להם
שני פתחים אחד
לגינה ואחד לביתן, u-pasach la-hem shenei pesachim echad le-gina ve-echad le-beisan, and
then you could like at a good party you can you know
mosey around, you can take a little walk. So you had a
door open into the garden if you wanted to walk in the
garden while you were having your drinks and hors d'oeuvres or you
could take a little walk and have a little you know tour
of the house, go into the castle. Okay, חור כרפס ותכלת, chur
karpas u-secheiles, so
now we're on to the various you know tapestries and other things.
So חור כרפס ותכלת, chur karpas u-secheiles, which is you know some
types of various linens and blue. So מאי חור? mai chur? What
is this חור? chur? רב אמר חרי חרי, Rav amar chari chari,
it was some fine type of stitching and needlework. ושמואל אמר מילת
לבנה הציע להם, u-Shmuel amar milas levanah hitzia la-hem, no, like white
is חור chur from חוור chivar from white as opposed to חור
chor from holes which is needlework. He's reading it from white, it
was white silk that he laid out for them. Okay, so that's
חור. chur. What's כרפס? karpas? So it's the thing you dip on
Pesach. So אמר רב יוסף בר חנינא כרים של פסים, amar Rav
Yosef bar Chanina karim shel pasim, that was cushions of velvet. על
גלילי כסף al gelilei chesef on pillars of silver, ועמודי שש ve-amudei
sheish and you know and pillars of marble, מטות זהב וכסף, motos
zahav va-chesef, so and beds of gold and silver. תני רב יהודה
אומר הראוי לכסף לכסף, tani Rav Yehudah omer ha-rauy le-chesef le-chesef, same
idea before, those that were deserving you know at a lower level
they got the silver beds, הראוי לזהב לזהב, ha-rauy le-zahav le-zahav, and
those that were got you know at the higher level they got
the gold beds. אמר לו רבי נחמיה, amar lo Rabi Nechemyah, Rabi
Nechemyah said, אם כן אתה מטיל קנאה בסעודה, im kein atah metil
kinah bi-seudah, so now you're going to have people jealous, ah he
gets the gold bed and I only got the silver bed, that's
not a good way to have a party. אלא הם של כסף
ורגליהם של זהב, ela heim shel chesef ve-ragleihem shel zahav, they were
both, you had silver and the legs were gold. Of course who's
looking at the legs? You would think the legs would be silver,
they'd be gold but that's a lot more expensive anyway. תוספות Tosafos
asks a question, if you look at תוספות Tosafos interesting, אתה מטיל
קנאה. atah metil kinah. תוספות Tosafos says ואם תאמר למאן דאמר לעיל
הראוי לגינה לגינה הראוי לחצר לחצר, ve-im tomar le-man de-amar le-eil ha-rauy
le-gina le-gina ha-rauy le-chatzer le-chatzer,
why wasn't this objection raised before when it said they were in
different locations? אם כן אתה מטיל קנאה בסעודה. im kein atah metil
kinah bi-seudah. So it says יש לומר דסבירא ליה דכיון דלא הוו
חזו זה את זה ליכא קנאה. yeish lomar de-sevira lei de-keivan de-lo
havu chazu zeh es zeh leika kinah. No, it was it was
huge, so you didn't see who was in the courtyard who was
in the I mean you still probably got a little upset, why
am I only going there and that person is getting sent to
that place but okay it wasn't as bad if it wasn't like
in your face.
So we think it's like a house, a big house with a
backyard, a garden, but it must have been like expansive like 20
blocks by 20 blocks.
Right. Reminded me of Gatsby's... Gatsby's... the world. You ever try to
make seating arrangements at a...?
That's a good point. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara בהט ושש. bahat va-sheish. בהט ושש bahat va-sheish which is
like I don't know green and white green and white marble is
how the English translates it. But let's see what the גמרא does
with this word בהט. bahat. אמר רב אסי אבנים שמתחטטות על בעליהן,
amar Rav Asi avanim she-mis-chatetos al ba-aleihen,
precious stones that are מתחטטות mis-chatetos on their owners. Whole discussion what
that means, sparkles, shine, רש״י Rashi says it means it forces their
owners to seek after them, they're very rare and precious. וכן הוא
אומר אבני נזר מתנוססות על אדמתו, ve-chein hu omer avnei nezer mis-nosesos
al admaso,
stones of the crown, crown jewels that are lifted over or or
sparkle over the land. And רש״י Rashi says that word also מתנוססות
mis-nosesos also means from the word of like ניסיון nisayon that require
an enormous amount of effort in order to find them. Okay. ודר
וסוחרת. ve-dar ve-sochares. Let's see what those are. רב אמר דרי דרי,
Rav amar dari dari, rows and rows of presumably like precious stones.
Okay.
ושמואל אמר אבן טובה יש בכרכי הים, u-Shmuel amar even tovah yeish
be-karchei ha-yam, there's a very precious stone over you know in the
in the foreign isles, ודרה שמה, ve-darah shemah, its name was דרה.
darah. So דר dar is the name of a precious stone. הושיבה
באמצע סעודה ומאירה להם כצהריים, hoshivah be-emtza seudah u-meirah la-hem ke-tzohorayim, which
seems to be play on the word of סוחרת sochares and צהריים.
tzohorayim. And it was it shone for them like the like the
middle of the day, like it was so bright this precious stone.
Okay.
דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא שקרא דרור לכל בעלי סחורה, de-vei Rabi Yishmael
tana she-kara deror le-chol ba-alei sechorah, going back to like the end
of the מגילה Megilla or going to the end of the מגילה
Megillah where he calls a you know he waives the taxes. So
here he says ודר וסוחרת ve-dar ve-sochares is not a precious stone,
it's a policy. He basically called דרור deror to בעלי סחורה. ba-alei
sechorah. He freedom to the merchants, he basically you know had it
said you know
removed the taxes on imports. So that was ודר וסוחרת. ve-dar ve-sochares.
So everybody was very happy. Okay, the בעלי סחורה *Ba'alei Sechorah*. והשקות
בכלי זהב וכלים מכלים שונים *Vehashkot biklei zahav vekeilim mikeilim shonim*, drinking
from golden vessels and different and different types of vessels, משונים מבעי
ליה *meshunim miba'ei leih*, since שונים *shonim* which means like from the
word שונה *shoneh* to repeat, it should have said משונים *meshunim*, different.
אמר רבא amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, יצתה בת קול ואמרה להם *yatzta
bat kol ve'amrah lahem*, a heavenly voice came out and said to
them, ראשונים כלו מפני כלים *rishonim kallu mipnei keilim*, the early ones,
Belshazzar like we set the stage yesterday, they were destroyed because they
used the Temple's vessels, ואתם שונים בהם *ve'atem shonim bahem*, and you're
repeating the sin, so from the word שני *sheni* and לשנות *lishnot*
to repeat and not just שונים *shonim* to be different. And again,
so here anchoring that earlier story of using the vessels in this
verse of כלים שונים *keilim shonim*, which is why we read it
with a different trop. Replicate, to duplicate. ויין מלכות *Veyein malchut*, wine
of the king, רב *rav* was plentiful. אמר רב *Amar Rav*, מלמד
שכל אחד ואחד השקוהו יין שגדול ממנו בשנים *melamed shekol echad ve'echad
hishquhu yayin shegadol mimenu beshanim*. So יין מלכות רב *yein malchut rav*
does not mean here plentiful, but means like older, is the way
he's reading it. Everybody drank wine older than his own age. והשתיה
כדת *Vehashtiyah khadat* and the drinking was according to the law, אין
אונס *ein ones*, nobody was forced, it was appropriate, no compulsion. So
מאי כדת *mai khadat*, what does it mean כדת *khadat* according to
the rule? אמר רב חנן משום רבי מאיר *Amar Rav Chanan mishum
Rabbi Meir*, כדת של תורה *khadat shel Torah*, following the rule of
the Torah. מה דת של תורה אכילה מרובה משתיה *mah dat shel
Torah achilah merubah mishtiyah*, the same way the Torah, eating is greater
than drinking, Rashi and Tosafot says this means that the food you
put on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*, the קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot* and the grain
offerings are much, much greater in proportion to the drinking, אף סעודתו
של אותו רשע אכילה מרובה משתיה *af se'udato shel oto rasha achilah
merubah mishtiyah*, even in that wicked man's meal, the eating was greater
than the drinking. So this is okay, that's nice. So it wasn't
just סתם *stam* a drinking party like one wonders, why say something
like this? Sounds like it's saying a nice thing about Achashverosh. So
I could just speculate again, I don't know about all these comments
how much sort of they're just like okay, saying something about the
verse even if it's not deeply meaningful. But I would just speculate
two possible points about this. One is Achashverosh is coming again to
like usurp the whole Beit Hamikdash, like you know, power and centrality.
It was within that idea. So he wears the vessels of the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol*, he uses the כלים *keilim*, he's
even making, you know, his, you know, sort of like they what
did they used to say like Vilna was the Jerusalem of, so
you know, so here he's making Shushan the new Jerusalem. He's, you
know, and he's the Kohen Gadol. So even in his סעודה *se'udah*,
he's somewhat replicating like what they would do on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*.
There'd be food, there'd be drinks, appropriate proportions. So sort of seeing
him in that sort of type of usurping role. The other possibility
is also because of, you know, and again, one wonders I might
be I might be retroprojecting here, but you know, the earlier Gemara
discussion before about drinking in the סעודה *se'udah* and חייב איניש לבסומי
*chayav inish levasumei* but then also pulling back a little with that
whole story of Rabbah and Rabbi Zeira. You know, how much do
we understand that our, you know, משתה ושמחה ויום טוב *mishteh vesimchah
veyom tov* on Purim, how much is the emphasis on the drinking
and how much is the emphasis on the סעודה *se'udah* and what
type of appropriate like balance do we have between them? So the
Gemara here might be somewhat sort of setting the stage although the
פסוקים *pesukim* emphasize the משתה *mishteh*, the Gemara is telling you that
actually the סעודה *se'udah* was much more central or proportionally much larger
than the actual amount of drinking. Charlie, what did you want to
say?
I was just going to say, so Christianity and Islam were not
the first attempts at supersessionism.
Oh, there you go. Exactly. All right. So the Gemara says like
this.
Okay. אין
אונס *ein ones*, nobody was forced. אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar*,
מלמד שכל אחד ואחד השקוהו מיין מדינתו *melamed shekol echad ve'echad hishquhu
miyein medinato*. Everybody was given wine from that was his own country
so nobody was sort of pressured or given wine that would feel
like you know like an imposition on them, hard for them to
drink and something that they didn't really that was that was not
pleasant and they didn't really want to be drinking.
Kosher wine. לעשות כרצון איש ואיש kirtzon ish va-ish.
*La'asot kirtzon ish va'ish*, to do like the will of every man.
אמר רבא amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, לעשות כרצון מרדכי Mordechai והמן *la'asot
kirtzon Mordechai veHaman*, like to do the will of Mordechai and Haman.
מרדכי Mordechai? דכתיב dechsiv, איש יהודי *Mordechai dikhtiv ish Yehudi*, the Jewish
man, right? המן Haman איש צר ואויב *Haman ish tzar ve'oyev*. So
they're called איש *ish* and איש *ish*. Now what does this mean,
the desire of Mordechai and Haman? So Rashi says it means Mordechai
and Haman were the wine stewards. Okay, the Maharsha says, what do
you mean? But the desire of every man is the desire of
the people drinking the wine, not the desire of the people serving
the wine. So Rashi says, well no, Mordechai and Haman were told
to give everybody the wine that they want. Anyway, it's a hard
read. So the Maharsha says, no, it means that the desire of
the people drinking the wine, but he sees Mordechai and Haman here
being just sort of stand-ins for meaning like people of all different
nations. That no matter what nation you were part of, whether you
were a Mordechai or whether you were a Haman, you know, your
needs were taken care of in terms of what you wanted to
drink. I wonder if the midrash if the Gemara here is actually
leaving the סעודה *se'udah* for the moment and talking about a theme
that we're going to hear later, you know, this gets to the
ארור המן Haman וברוך *arur Haman uvaruch*... ברוך מרדכי Mordechai issues, which
is about how the story of the מגילה Megillah, was not all
המן's Haman fault as well, you know, to some degree it was
מרדכי's Mordechai fault also according to the גמרא, you know, the way
that he refused to bow down to המן Haman and so on,
and even in the simple read of the מגילה, Megillah, you know,
he was always, I mean, no, the גמרא says it, that's, that
is the מגילה, Megillah, but the גמרא is because of the whole
issue about the idol and so on. But in the, but in
the, you know, even in the פשט peshat of the מגילה, Megillah
right, he's like, it seems a little bit he's getting in המן's
face. You know, he's not bowing down, other people are bowing down,
why not bowing down? And so the גמרא, as I said, right.
So how much is, is this a little bit like all about
מרדכי? You know, you know, מרדכי was the, you know, was the
reason that set all these things into motion. So some want to
say that that gets back into the גמרא as I said about,
you know, בין ארור המן לברוך מרדכי, Bein Arur Haman le-Baruch Mordechai,
like it's so clear here who really was to blame and who
really was the bad guy and so on. So that might be
a little bit like the story of the מגילה Megillah is כרצון
איש ואיש. It's not just רצון המן, ratzon Haman, it's also רצון
מרדכי, ratzon Mordechai, like this whole thing, you know, was coming from
equally from the acts and from the, the will of both of
them. So,
okay. So the גמרא says like this. Okay. גם ושתי המלכה, Gam
Vashti ha-Malka,
now we get to some of the famous מדרשים midrashim about ושתי.
Vashti. עשתה משתה נשים, astah mishteh nashim, she made a drinking party
for the women. בית המלכות, beit ha-malkhut, in the king's house, in
the castle. בית הנשים מיבעי ליה, beit ha-nashim mi-ba'ei lei, she should
be, she should have had the women's party in the women's house.
What are you doing having the women's party in the castle where
the men are? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava ששניהם לדבר עבירה נתכוונו.
she-shneihem li-dvar aveira nitkavnu. Both of them were had intent for sin.
Both of them, so which means, why was she in the castle?
Because they were, you know, they were interested in getting together with
the men in the castle. So they all had sex on their
mind. והיינו דאמרי אינשי, ve-haynu de-amrei inshi, that's what people say, איהו
בקרי ואיתתיה בבוציני. ihu be-karei ittei be-butzinei.
He has like, you know, the man has, has, has his gourds
and the woman has her gourds, which basically is a way of
saying like good for the goose, good for the gander, I think
would be the contemporary idiom. Okay, so anyway, the both, they both
have that on their mind and that's why it's all happening in
the same, in the same basic space. ויהי ביום השביעי כטוב לב
המלך ביין, vayehi bayom ha-shevi'i ke-tov lev ha-melekh bayayin, on day seven
when the king's heart was, was joyous with wine. So the גמרא
says, אטו עד השתא לא טב ליביה בחמרא? a-tu ad hashta lo
tav libei be-khamra? Wait a minute, until now his heart was not
good with wine? He's been drinking for seven days. So אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, יום השביעי שבת היה. yom ha-shevi'i Shabbat haya. So it
was שבת, Shabbat, יום השביעי yom ha-shevi'i was שבת, Shabbat, שישראל אוכלים
ושותים, she-Yisrael okhlim ve-shotim, when, when ישראל eat and drink on שבת,
Shabbat, מתחילים בדברי תורה
ובדברי תשבחות. matkhilin be-divrei Torah ve-divrei tishbakhot. They talk over, over the
פרשה, parsha, they sing some זמירות. zemirot. So for them on שבת,
Shabbat, that type of being in a positive state encourages, you know,
appropriate types of, of, of talk and of, and, and discourse and
so on. עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, oveidei kokhavim u-mazalot, but the idolaters, שאוכלים
ושותים אין מתחילים אלא בדברי תפלות, she-okhlim ve-shotim ein matkhilin ella be-divrei
tiflut, when they eat and drink, what do they talk about? Nonsense.
וכן בסעודתו של אותו רשע, ve-khen bi-seudato shel oto rasha, and the
same with that wicked man's, the meal. הללו אומרים, hallalu omrim, and
what would they talk about? They talk about women. מדיות נאות, midiyot
na'ot, this group would say, oh, the מדי Median women, they're the
most beautiful. והללו אומרים פרסיות נאות, ve-hallalu omrim Parsiyot na'ot, and the
others would say the פרסי Persian women, they're the most beautiful. אמר
להם אחשורוש, amar lahem Akhashverosh, and אחשורוש Akhashverosh said, כלי שאני משתמש
בו, kli she-ani mishtamesh bo, the vessel that I use, right, being
very vulgar, אינו לא מדי ולא פרסי אלא כשדי. eino lo Madai
ve-lo Parsi ella Kasdi. Isn't a מדי and isn't פרסי, Persian, but
it's
כשדי. Kasdian.
ורצונכם לראותה? u-retzonkhem lir'otah? לראותה? lir'otah?
Would you like to see this vessel?
Meaning ושתי, Vashti, his wife. אמרו לו אין, ameru lo in, yes,
ובלבד שתהא ערומה. u-belvad she-te'hei arumah. But we got to really see
her, she has to be naked. שבמידה שאדם מודד בה מודדין לו,
she-b'midah she-adam moded bah modedin lo, and
the measure that a person deals out, that's the measure that they
are, is measured for them. Now not talking about אחשורוש, Akhashverosh, but
talking about ושתי. Vashti. מלמד שהייתה ושתי הרשעה melamed she-hayta Vashti ha-rasha
מביאה בנות ישראל ומעסיטן ערומות, mevi'ah benot Yisrael u-ma'asitan arumot, because all
of this teaches you, I mean, it teaches you because we're starting
from the principle and working backwards, but okay, it teaches you that
ושתי Vashti would take young בנות ישראל benot Yisrael and strip them
naked, ועושה בהן מלאכה בשבת, ve-osah ban melakha be-Shabbat, and force them
to serve her and work for her on שבת. Shabbat. And therefore
she also was stripped naked on שבת. Shabbat. היינו דכתיב, haynu di-ktiv,
now of course what's not, so that's the whole מידה כנגד מידה.
midah k'neged midah. What it doesn't explain is how come it took
him seven days to get to טוב לב המלך. tov lev ha-melekh.
I mean, it's sort of, sort of saying, well maybe he wasn't
in a good mood before that, but maybe anyway this waited for
seven days because in order, the whole thing, it should be שבת
Shabbat and it should be מידה כנגד מידה. midah k'neged midah. Or
I don't know, somehow because שבת Shabbat is a day that Jews
enjoy themselves, somehow even though he had been drinking for six days,
he didn't really start getting into it until שבת Shabbat itself. Anyway,
the question it raised wasn't fully answered, but it seems it was
more interested in getting to this point than in answering why it
took him seven days to get in a good mood.
Yes, and then in the גמרא it says it wasn't just seven
days of the party, it was seven days of the week. Oh.
That says it too. You're right.
I just oh just ביום השביעי Bayom Hashevi'i means on שבת Shabbos
when
but but right it still wouldn't explain whatever that day I don't
think it's going that far to read it that way. Anyway but
right true true. Okay so it didn't really answer why it took
him seven days but anyway we got to this whole point about
שבת. Shabbos. Okay. והנה זכר ויהי אחרי הדברים האלה כשך חמת המלך
אחשורוש Vehineh zachar vayehi acharei hadevarim ha'eleh keshach chamat hamelech Achashverosh because
זכר את ושתי ואת אשר עשתה ואת אשר נגזר עליה. zachar et
Vashti ve'et asher astah ve'et asher nigzar aleiha. So why does it
say he remembered ושתי Vashti what she did and what he was
נגזר nigzar on her? כשם שעשתה כך נגזר עליה. Keshem she'astah kach
nigzar aleiha. So it's אשר עשתה ואשר נגזר עליה. asher astah va'asher
nigzar aleiha. What she had done in the past was what was
נגזר nigzar on her from God that she should appear naked meaning
not what she had done just now was נגזר nigzar on her
from מרדכי but it gets back to the מידה כנגד מידה. middah
keneged middah. Okay. ותמאן המלכה ושתי Vatema'en hamalkah Vashti now ושתי Vashti
he wants her to come להראות העמים והשרים את יפיה leharot ha'amim
vehasarim et yafyah which the גמרא now has added means naked and
ושתי Vashti refused. Okay.
So the הגהות הרמ"א Hagahot Ha'Rama has a nice or the הגר"א
HaGra has a nice let's see הגר"א HaGra has a nice סברא
sevarah of this by the way because he says that when אחשורוש
Achashverosh calls her it says what does it say? ויאמר המלך להביא
את ושתי המלכה. Vayomer hamelech lehavi et Vashti hamalkah. So first it
says ושתי Vashti and then it says מלכה. malkah. And then when
she responds ותמאן המלכה ושתי Vatema'en hamalkah Vashti the Queen ושתי. Vashti.
So he says that אחשורוש Achashverosh was saying to her like hey
you know you're ושתי Vashti you're just a queen second you're just
a queen because you're married to me so you have to listen
to what I say. And she responded back and she said nobody
I'm the queen and we'll see in the גמרא the גמרא understands
that ושתי Vashti was a granddaughter of נבוכדנצר and what ושתי Vashti
was saying back was you're just king because you're married to me
it's not the other way around. So anyway he notes the reversal
of whether it's המלכה ושתי Hamalkah Vashti or ושתי המלכה. Vashti hamalkah.
ותמאן המלכה ושתי. Vatema'en hamalkah Vashti. מכדי פריצותא הואי. Michdi peritzuta havai.
She was you know licentious so she was having this party as
we said they were all thinking about talking about sex so דאמר
מר שניהם לדבר עבירה נתכוונו De'amar mar shenehem lidevar aveirah nitkavnu they
were both planning on all of this אמאי לא אתאי? Amai lo
atai? Why wouldn't she come? Doesn't mean she wanted to be objectified
but okay. אמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא מלמד שפרחה בה צרעת. Amar
Rabi Yosi bar Chanina melamed sheparchah bah tzara'at. Okay so something happened
she would have come but something disfigured she got a rash she
got צרעת. tzara'at. רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק because it's by צרעת
tzara'at it says there's another פסוק that says נגזר. nigzar. Where's the
פסוק? רש"י Rashi says or תוספות Tosafot quotes ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
By עוזיהו Uziyahu it says נגזר מבית ה' nigzar mibeit Hashem so
אשר נגזר עליה asher nigzar aleiha reading that to mean that there's
something that was נגזר nigzar meaning that there was this צרעת. tzara'at.
במתניתא תנא Bematnita tana and a ברייתא Beraisa we taught בא גבריאל
ועשה לה זנב. Ba Gavriel ve'asah lah zanav. She got a tail
okay which is getting a little fantastic in terms of all
this. מהרש"א Maharsha suggests or quotes somebody he doesn't agree with it
but quotes somebody that it doesn't have to literally mean a tail
it just means some type of a growth. She got some type
of a disfiguring growth. Okay and therefore that's the only reason she
didn't want to come. ויקצוף המלך מאד Vayiktzof hamelech me'od and the
king got very angry. אמאי דלקה ביה כולי האי? Amai dalkah beih
kulei hai? Why'd he get so angry? I mean it seems like
you know okay she was refused but why'd he get so worked
up? אמר רבא שלחה ליה shalchah leih because here's what ושתי Vashti
sent him and this gets back to that הגר"א HaGra I was
telling you before about you know what the subtext of their demand
and
refusal. בר אהוריא דאבא Bar ahorya de'abba you are the like you
know the stable boy of my father.
אבא לקבל אלפא חמרא שתי Abba lekabel alfa chamra shatei my father
so I think I said grandfather before father anyway she's the daughter
of נבוכדנצר. Anyway my father לקבל אלפא חמרא שתי lekabel alfa chamra
shatei he could drink a thousand you know flasks of wine ולא
רוי velo ravi he wouldn't get drunk. והאי גברא Vehai gavra this
guy you אשתית
בחמרא מיהא ishtit bechamra miha you got drunk with your wine. So
she was basically mocking him dispoofing him you know you tell me
to come psh you're my father's stable boy you're not even a
real king you can't even hold your
liquor. So מיהא? miha? You got drunk with your wine. וחמתו בערה
בו Vachamato ba'arah bo his anger fired within him. ויאמר המלך לחכמים
Vayomer hamelech lachachamim so the king said to the sages. מאן חכמים?
Man chachamim? So who were the sages? Obviously רבנן Rabanan the rabbis.
Who else did he go to but the rabbis? יודעי העתים yodei
ha'itim they knew the times שיודעים לעבר שנים ולקבוע חדשים sheyodim le'aber
shanim velikboa chadashim they know how to make the times. So אמר
להו amar lehu by the way the other thing that we should
note about this whole thing was not you know in the whole
thing about שבת Shabbos and the whole thing about before about the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and now about the רבנן Rabanan is not
just like the mocking but it's sort of making all of this
like here we have the King of Persia right the King of
the entire civilized world and what we're doing is as we are
always doing is we're situating all of this really into the into
Jewish history. Meaning it's not just it intersected with Jewish history it's
all part the whole world history is really a Jewish history right?
So you
know everything is through the the real story of history is the
story of Jewish history. And everything else is just part of that
story. So this is sort of what it's doing as well here,
right? The whole story about אחשורוש, Achashveirosh, all אחשורוש Achashveirosh could be
thinking about was the 70 years of דניאל Daniel. and he's waiting
for the time and he's showing that it's not being fulfilled, right?
So it's making אחשורוש Achashveirosh all about, like his all of his
concerns centered around sort of the Jewish history. So here too, you
know, it's really doing the same thing. Who do you go to?
You got a question? Of course you got to the rabbis, you
know? So that's sort of, it just is a way of, like
I think completely changing our view, like the the like the New
Yorker's view of the world, you know? Like everything takes place through
the lens of Jewish history. That's the perfect perspective.
Do you hear this as satirical?
Or are we trying to be explanatory?
Well,
I don't know if I'd say satirical or explanatory, meaning, I you
know,
I don't know. I don't see this necessarily as an intentional satire,
but what I do see this is as a taking of the
story of the מגילה and not just saying פשט, pshat, but trying
to sort of frame it through a rabbinic lens and to sort
of give it historical meaning through a rabbinic lens. So he looked
at the story and saying, oh, all this was happening because of
the way ושתי Vashti misused the Jewish women and the way אחשורוש
Achashveirosh misused the כלים or whatever, it shapes your whole understanding of
history. So I don't know if that's not satire and that's not
explanatory.
I don't know if we can take another step. Oh. So if
you want to say the inside story of the palace that the
king and the and the and the queen have a terrible relationship,
right, he's tough on him, right, I mean you could totally hear
that today, right, that they both have they both have issues, you
could totally hear that that might be explanatory. Then you get to
that he consults the rabbis, is that satire, is that something real,
that she grows a tail, is that satire, is that something real?
Right. Right. Right, so at what stage, right, that's true, like are
there some of these statements that are just said for like the
absurd and the satiric effect? It's possible, you know? I don't get
a sense that that's the over larger theme here, but certainly some
of the statements like the tail statements or whatever, I think it's
possible. You know, but I don't know, I don't have an I
don't have
an eye for it.
You don't know that Jewish comedy. Right. Right, I do know I
do know people sometimes say, like in some of these discussions, every
now and then they'll throw like a joke comment or a satiric
comment or something, so keep people awake, so it's possible, like but
yeah, was there another comment?
Yeah. The very next verse after it says it says that he
consults the sages, it's a list of seven verses.
All right, so let's take a look. Okay. So... ויאמר... Vayomer... אמר
להו... amar lehu... he said to them, דיינו לי, dayinu li, judge
for me. אמרו, amru, they said to him, היכי נעביד, haichi naavid,
now what can we do? נימא ליה קטלה, nima leh katla, if
we tell her to tell him to kill her, למחר פסיק ליה
חמריה, lemachar pasik leh chamrei, so by tomorrow he'll he'll sober up,
the wine will
stop, ובעי לה מינן, uvaei lah minan, he'll say and he'll demand
her from us, he'll say how did you let me kill her?
Here's my queen. נימא ליה שבקה, nima leh shavka, tell him to
let it go, קא מזלזלה במלכותא, ka mezalzela bemalchuta, then she was
to you know, she was disrespecting the kingship and that will we'll
be held accountable for letting that go. אמרו ליה, amru leh, so
they ducked, מיום שחרב בית המקדש וגלינו מארצנו ניטלה עצה ממנו ואין
אנו יודעים לדון דיני נפשות. miyom shecharav beis hamikdash vegalinu meartzeinu nittla
eitza mimmenu ve-ein anu yodim ladun dinei nefashos. From the time the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, was destroyed, we don't have the you know
we're not as wise as we used to be and we're not
able to judge דיני נפשות, dinei nefashos, going back to the destruction
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash theme and maybe like a subtle
hint, you could help this out by letting us rebuild the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash Anyway, זיל לגבי עמון ומואב דיתבי בדוכתייהו, zil legabei
amon umoav deyasvi beduchtayeihu, go to other nations, עמון Amon and מואב,
Moav, they've never exiled, כחמרא דיתיב על דורדייהו, kachamra deyasiv al durdeiyeihu,
like wine that sits on its like lees, you know, and that's
unsettled wine, and they וטעמא אמרו ליה, vetaama amru leh, and they
and and either means they, the עמון Amon and מואב Moav gave
gave the king טעם, taam, reason, which is also taste of wine,
or the גמרא is commenting that that which the sages said to
אחשורוש, Achashveirosh, they said a good thing, דכתיב, as the verse says,
שאנן מואב מנעוריו ושוקט הוא על שמריו, shaanan moav mineurav veshokeit hu
al shemarav, this whole metaphor of wine by מואב Moav is in
this פסוק. מואב Moav has been tranquil from its youth and it's
been on its like the lees of the wine, the grapes, ולא
הורק מכלי אל כלי, velo hurak mikli el kli, has not been
exiled, has not been poured from one vessel to the next, ובגולה
לא הלך, uvagola lo halach, has not gone into exile, על כן
עמד טעמו בו וריחו לא נמר, al kein amad taamo bo voreicho
lo namar, therefore its taste remains and its odor has not been
removed. Okay, so he says so he so they duck, ask someone
else. מיד והקרוב אליו כרשנא שתר אדמתא תרשיש. miyad vehakarov eilav karshena
sheisatar admasa tarshish. אמר רבי לוי, amar rabbi levi, כל פסוק זה
על שום קרבנות נאמר. kol pasuk zeh al shum korbanos ne'emar. So
again, this whole בית המקדש theme, this whole פסוק is about הקרוב,
hakorov,
right? קרוב, korov, קרבן, korban, so it's all about קרבנות. korbanos, Now,
כרשנא... karshena... So the heavenly angels said to God, רבונו של עולם,
Ribbono Shel Olam, כלום הקריבו לפניך כרים בני שנה? klum hikrivu lifanecha
karim bnei shana? So כרשנא, Kar-shena, have these non-Jews ever offered like
to you, like the Jews offered to you, like lambs a year
old כדרך שהקריבו ישראל לפניך? kederach shehikrivu Yisrael lifanecha? שתר, Shetar, what's
שתר? Shetar? כלום הקריבו לפניך שתי תורים, klum hikrivu lifanecha shtei torim,
שתי תורים, shtei torim, שתר. Shetar. אדמתא, Admasa, כלום בנו לפניך מזבח
אדמה, klum banu lifanecha mizbach adama, did they ever build for you
an altar of dirt? תרשיש, Tarshish, כלום שימשו לפניך בבגדי כהונה, klum
shimshu lifanecha bevigdei kehuna, did they ever serve you with בגדי כהונה?
bigdei kehuna? We know that Ahasuerus usurped the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna,
but did they ever serve you with בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehuna? דכתיב
ביה תרשיש ושהם וישפה, dichtiv bei tarshish veshoham veyashpei, it says תרשיש
Tarshish was one of the jewels, you know, for the כהן גדול.
מרס, Meres, כלום מירסו בדם לפניך, klum mirsu bedam lifanecha, did they
ever stir the blood before you? מרסנא, Marsena, כלום מירסו במנחות לפניך,
klum mirsu bemenachos lifanecha, did they ever stir the מנחות menachos to
mix them up, you know you mix up the flour with the
oil. ממוכן, Memuchan, כלום הכינו שולחן לפניך, klum hechinu shulchan lifanecha, did
they ever put a table before you? So you know obviously so
this was them so to speak, God, you gotta get involved here
and help the Jewish people. Now you know because this obviously was
a story that led to Esther, so you gotta sort of plant
Esther here because bad things are coming and you know and these
non-Jews you know look where they are in comparison to how the
Jews you know have served you in the past. But again quite
fascinating bringing up the whole issue of the קרבנות, which is not
currently the case
and but again that seems to be exactly the point that all
of this is part of the story of leading to the rebuilding
of the בית המקדש, similar to the story of the sages. We
don't have a בית המקדש so all of this is part of
that arc of history of the בית המקדש being destroyed and then
to be rebuilt.
Okay, so the גמרא is saying that each name that alliterates with
an עבודה, Avoda, that's the עבודה Avoda that they didn't do.
Didn't do. Right. So let's just read one more sentence about that.
ויאמר ממוכן, Vayomer Memuchan, תנא ממוכן זה המן. Tanna Memuchan zeh Haman.
ולמה נקרא שמו ממוכן, ulama nikra shemo memuchan, why was he called
ממוכן? Memuchan? שמוכן לפורענות, shemuchan lepuranus, because he was setting himself up
for bad things unintentionally. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, מכאן שהדיוט
קופץ בראש, mikan shehedyot kofetz berosh, so you see the minor person,
the layperson jumps to the head. He was the last guy on
the list, but he was so taken with himself that he had
to speak up first. להיות כל איש שורר בביתו ומדבר כלשון עמו,
lihyos kol ish sorer beveiso umedaber kilshen amo, so אמר רבא, אלמלא
אגרות הראשונות, ilmalei igros harishonos, were not for the first letters that
he sent out here at the beginning of the story, לא נשתייר
משונאיהם של ישראל, lo nishtayer mishoneihem shel Yisrael, משונאיהם של ישראל mishoneihem
shel Yisrael again, so survived not a bit, the Jews would have
been completely destroyed. Because once they got the permission to rise up
against the Jews, they wouldn't have waited till the 13th of Adar,
they would have acted on it right away, and that would have
been the end of the Jewish people. But the reason that later
letter did not have the power it did was because the earlier
letter was so foolish, it undermined Ahasuerus's authority. Why was the earlier
letter so foolish? אמרי כשקיבלו אגרות הראשונות, amri keshekiblu igros harishonos, when
they got the earlier letter people said, מאי האי דשדר לן, mai
hai deshadr lan, what is he sending to us?
להיות כל איש שורר בביתו, lihyos kol ish sorer beveiso, פשיטא אפילו
קרדא דזוזי פרדשכא ליהוי. pshita afilu karda dezuzi pardashcha lehvei. So what's
that phrase? Not master of the castle. What's the phrase? Master of
the house or something, a king in his castle?
King in his castle.
Anyway they have the stay there, even master of his own domain.
Okay. Anyway even like you know even like a lowly person in
his own house he's the head, he's the governor. So obviously this
is a stupid king, he doesn't even these edicts he's sending out
are foolish, and therefore they hesitated and they didn't act on it
immediately in the later letter, and that ultimately saved the Jews. Okay,
so just with I just want to end with one little תוספות
Tosafot on that point. If you look at תוספות Tosafot ממוכן, Memuchan,
תוספות Tosafot said, יש מדרש שהיה דניאל, yesh midrash shehaya Daniel, not
המן it was דניאל. ולפי שהיה נשוי לשרה שהיתה גדולה ממנו, ulfi
shehaya nasui lesara shehayesa gedola mimenu, and because he was married to
a noblewoman who was of higher status than him, שלא היה יכול
לכופפה לדבר כלשונו, shelo haya yachol lchofefa ledaber kilshono, that he couldn't
get her to speak his language, יעץ לעשות כן. ya'atz la'asos kein.
So this is all politics are personal, right? Because Daniel was married
to a woman who he couldn't get her to speak his language,
so he told Ahasuerus, you gotta tell all the households that the
wives have to listen to their husbands and speak their husbands' language.
That's a pretty wild... I'll tell you one other thing... hold on,
let me just turn this...